Emile Schaub-Koch Papers
Emile Schaub-Koch Papers
1933-1965
Schaub-Koch, Emile, 1890-
3.0 linear ft.
Papers of the Swiss art critic. Collection focuses on Schaub-Koch's interest in American sculptor Anna Hyatt Huntington.
149566
Biographical History
Emile Schaub-Koch (1890-?) was a Swiss art critic and author. He wrote extensively on American sculptor Anna Hyatt Huntington.
Born March 6, 1890 in Switzerland, Emile Schaub was educated in Paris at the École Supérieure Libre des Sciences, but made his name in the field of fine arts criticism. He married Anna Koch in 1914 and added her name to his, becoming Emile Schaub-Koch. They were married for more than 30 years, until her death in 1946, and had one adopted son.
Schaub-Koch was named honorary professor at the Université de France; he was a member of the editorial board of the International Studies of Science and Letters and an honorary member of many other scholarly European societies. He was awarded the Croix de Devouement by the government of Portugal, and by 1948 he had written over 250 publications on scientific and literary subjects as well as art criticism. In 1948 he became intensely interested in the work of American sculptor Anna Hyatt Huntington, and devoted the following years to writing books and articles about her work and its relationship to other art forms from earlier periods. Schaub-Koch did much to popularize Huntington's work in Europe, to the extent that she is better known abroad than in her own country. His works, written originally in French, have been translated into English, Spanish, Italian, and Portuguese.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Emile Schaub-Koch Papers include correspondence, photographs, manuscripts, and published materials both by and about Schaub-Koch.
Correspondence includes incoming notes, cards and letters. The majority are thank-you notes to Professor Schaub- Koch for complimentary copies of his books. The correspondence is in French, Spanish, Italian, and English, most from Europeans.
Photographs include pictures of Brookgreen Gardens, Anna Hyatt Huntington's sculpture garden and preserve in South Carolina; a picture of a portrait of Mrs. Huntington by Marion Boyd Allen; and numerous photographs of Mrs. Huntington's work, used by Professor Schaub-Koch as illustrations for his many books on her sculpture.
Manuscripts consists of a typescript article by Schaub-Koch, translated by Tere Rios, entitled "The work of Anna Hyatt Huntington." It is undated.
Published material consists of articles, books, clippings, and pamphlets by and about Professor Schaub-Koch and others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Photographs are subdivided by type; within that, photographs of Mrs. Huntington's work is arranged alphabetically by title of the piece. Published materials are subdivided by type; within that, they are arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
For additional Schaub-Koch correspondence and writings, see the
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Huntington, Anna Hyatt, 1876-1973.; Schaub-Koch, Emile, 1890-; Art criticism.; Art critics.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Art critics.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Emile Schaub-Koch, 1966.
Inventory
- Correspondence (incoming)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1952, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1954-1957, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1959-1961, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1962, 1964, 1965, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Brookgreen Gardens (Box 4)
  - Display (Box 4)
  - Portrait of Anna Hyatt Huntington, by Marion Boyd Allen (Box 4)
  - Works by Anna Hyatt Huntington, A-Z, 17 folders (Box 4)
- Manuscripts
  - The Work of Anna Hyatt Huntington / Emile Schaub-Koch, translated by Tere Rios (Box 5)
- Published material
  - Articles
    - About Emile Schaub-Koch (Box 5)
    - By Emile Schaub-Koch (Box 5)
    - About others (Box 5)
  - Books, by Emile Schaub-Koch
    - Anna Hyatt Huntington and the Hindu People (Box 5)
    - Anna Hyatt Huntington, Sculptor de la Vie (Box 5)
    - Hindu Art and the Art of Anna Hyatt Huntington (Box 5)
    - A obra animalista e monumental de Anna Hyatt Huntington (Box 5)
    - L'oeuvre d'Anna Hyatt Huntington (Box 6)
    - Physiologie Esthétique de l'oeuvre animalier d'Anna Hyatt Huntington (Box 6)
    - Valeurs de rappels d'esthétique comparative (Box 6)
    - Vie et modelage (Box 6)
  - Clippings
    - About Schaub-Koch (Box 6)
    - About others (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets
    - Extrait de la revue d'esthétique / Perigord, Monique (Box 6)
    - Invertebrata / Schaub-Koch, Emile (Box 6)